<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Bruno's Website of Things</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2023-08-30T17:33:13+01:00</updated><entry><title>Science and Sanity (not a review)</title><link href="/science-and-sanity-not-a-review.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-08-30T17:33:13+01:00</published><updated>2023-08-30T17:33:13+01:00</updated><author><name>Bruno Teles</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-08-30:/science-and-sanity-not-a-review.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Not really a review of a very long and technical book I haven't finished, but which has influence the way I use language and hence how I think. Something I'd like to get back to someday.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've never finished Science and Sanity, by Alfred Korzbski. I've barely made it a third of the way through, actually, having read it as closely as I possibly could, given the constraints of my life at the time. I'd say I made a proper attempt at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science and Sanity is an exposition of a system of thought, or a discipline, called General Semantics, which Korzybski founded. It's a massive book, and not an easy read, which uses language updates of his own making (such as a full stop to mean, roughly, etc.). Why he does this is explained in the book, and he has what he thinks is good reason for it. Since I have not even made it to the middle of the book, please read the below as characterizing what I understood of the book and the system rather than characterizing it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things the book does is it sets a group of changes in language which Korzybski proposes will make English a more "sane" language, in his use of the term, is synonimous with having the same structure of the world around. That, for him, is the structure of the universe as set out by scientific enquiry. Hence the title "Sience and Sanity". His most famous change is to proscribe the use of the verb to be in its capacity as verb of identity (basically, always, unless it's an auxiliary verb). The reasoning behind this is that verbs define relationships between things, and there's no such thing as an identity relationship, or at least, science hasn't found one in nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For William Burroughs, the adoption of this would lead to an end to war. I don't know if we can go that far, but I do recommend trying to rephrase any heated argument without recourse to the verb to be, and you'll feel immediately how much more difficult it is to draw battle lines and be upset. We generally fight for what something is, and, if we teach ourselves to refrain from thinking in those terms, we will be released from a profound burden - though we may have to acquire another burden, which, as the Spiderman would have it, is the responsibility that comes with power. A power to heal, perhaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These ideas are worth engaging with, I think, and experimenting with. Noam Chomsky, the famous linguist, said something to the effect of he read all of Korzybski and that it could all be summarised in the sentence "Be careful with what you say." Chomsky, of course, has read much more than me, understands the subject much better than me and meant his comments as a diss, I think. But what I would say is that what Korzbski has shown me is precisely that being careful with language is anything but trivial, and it can have profound, read world-changing, effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something to consider, I think.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reviews"></category></entry><entry><title>Games Arena: New project first week update</title><link href="/games-arena-new-project-first-week-update.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-08-30T17:03:09+01:00</published><updated>2023-08-30T17:03:09+01:00</updated><author><name>Bruno Teles</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-08-30:/games-arena-new-project-first-week-update.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Django web application, project name Games Arena, week one update.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm starting a new project in Django, which is to be the final project of my Web Development with Python and Javascript course. Unlike other projects of that course, this one I will be doing from scratch, with no seed code. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This first week, I have initialized the django project and created a screen to choose your nickname. Once you do, or if you already have logged in before, it will take you to the Games Arena proper, where you'll be able to see who else is online so you can choose people to play a game. All this is done via sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment, being online is implemented only as a button which allows players to make themselves available for a game, but I'm looking to implement a way for the server to tell who is and isn't online automatically. I'm looking to do this via Redis. More news on that, or on my failure to do so, on my next update, I hope.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Development Blog"></category></entry><entry><title>Website: New project using Pelican</title><link href="/website-new-project-using-pelican.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-08-28T18:03:45+01:00</published><updated>2023-08-28T18:03:45+01:00</updated><author><name>Bruno Teles</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-08-28:/website-new-project-using-pelican.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;First update on new project, creating a website using Pelican&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm making a static website (this one) in which to keep the different parts of my internet presence organised, and also to help me figure out who am am? (Not not am, must not say am).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm using Pelican, a Python static website generator, and Markdown for the pages. Pelican is very easy to use. Having written websites in clunkier ways (my previous website, which dates from the early 2000s, was written entirely on raw HTML) I found it a breeze to create the content, layout and articles. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Documentation is short and very well written, with about everything you might need from a website like this. It lends itself to being configured to automate lots of things (such as the article type, category, date of publication and modification) as well as automatically reacting to a new file and, making the output HTML and serving it. So, after just a few tweaks, you're just writing really simple markdown files and saving them. This is a way of working I appreciate, but I'm also reassured I can change the fields being written automatically by manually including them, which I have been making use of to create an archive of past projects based on when I first released them, rather than the date of creation of the article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I've initialized my project, configured it to do what I need it to do, been trying out different themes and different functionalities. I like the way there's a base configuration that gets changed based on a smaller, easily readable file (at least so far, as I haven't changed that many parameters) which sets out what you need for testing and that there's a further file with config for when you actually go ahead and publish it. So far, it reads well and works well. Haven't brought it live yet, though, as I want to flesh out the content a little better before I do that, so I'll put a note here detailing how that went&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also been using virtualenv to create a virtual environment where I have installed pelican and markdown. This is something I plan to do going forward on other projects, as it is a much neater way to ensure you have what you need for a particular usecase without messing with other projects. I will be using that on the web app I'm developing as well, especially as I'll be working with a database (Redis) which I haven't used before, and I want to make sure I don't break things in the base configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's all for now!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Development Blog"></category></entry><entry><title>Do lots cry?</title><link href="/do-lots-cry.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-08-27T09:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-08-27T18:19:22+01:00</updated><author><name>Bruno Teles</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-08-27:/do-lots-cry.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Book review of The Crying of Lot 49, by Thomas Pynchon&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Spoilerish review of Thomas Pynchon's "The Crying of Lot 49". I wouldn't worry too much about spoilers here, but if you wnat to go without knowing absolutely anything, just go ahead and read it (spoiler for the review: I'm going to recommend it!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's funny. It's terrifying in a strange way, like a ghost story made believable. It is a virtuoso display of use of words, of the art of writing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's framed essentially as a detective novel, though there are no detectives, but a lowly executor of a will whose attempt at sorting the dead person's estate uncovers a great conspiracy or perhaps not quite. The novel lives for, perhaps demonstrate, this quantum-like "the electron is here and not here until we observe ita and collapse the wave function", in that we're never quite sure the conspiracy being uncovered is in any way real, and not the product of a paranoid mind (whose paranoid mind, the dead man or the executor, is also up for grabs.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also impossible not to mention the superb finale, though it would be too much to just explain it outright. Let us just say that, same as our main character uncovers the mystery, we uncover the mystery of the book title itself, a seemingly nonsensical sentence which we will, by the end, be assured not just of its meaning, but mainly, of its terrific importance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though perhaps not my favourite of the three Pynchon's I have read ("Bleeding Edge" takes that spot), it's short, and it does things some things too well, too well (by which I mean no other book does it quite like that) that it's essential to give it go. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So no excuses! Get it now at your local library or wherever you get your books.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reviews"></category></entry><entry><title>Living Compost</title><link href="/living-compost.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-04-10T10:20:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-04-10T19:30:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Bruno Teles</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-04-10:/living-compost.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Short documentary I wrote and directed, about East Sussex's Compost Club&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Living Compost - a day with Compost Club is a short documentary about Compost Club, a social enterprise company collecting food waste around East Sussex and transforming it into high-quality compost. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Language: English&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/IHjVMAmRB9c?si=WTOl3Cb9s7RM-NH0" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><category term="Videos"></category></entry><entry><title>Animation snippets</title><link href="/animation-snippets.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-01-10T10:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-10T19:30:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Bruno Teles</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-01-10:/animation-snippets.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here's the links to different animation I made throughout the years. These are all less than one minute in length. Language: English&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here's the links to different animation I made throughout the years. These are all less than one minute in length and the intention is comedic. Whether it's funny or not, well, that's not really for me to say. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Languages: English&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trailer to the greatest movie ever made&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4yLWYM5aG0k?si=jKt2QkCumYMmC5oQ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another trailer to another greatest movie ever made&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gzAMEjMtJDg?si=OMNTuXQQIt1iJsFg" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teamwork&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/s6oL9kCkYJA?si=ZCJAKqoSoPbrw8PK" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;December 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gA0exZVK9sA?si=WHp1wDjwMwKGXPZf" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;iDEaS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.newgrounds.com/content/embed.php?id=SjWBc" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starlings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.newgrounds.com/content/embed.php?id=SjZFb" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh nevermind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Nm_-EKRpxwQ?si=sRfebORI725r_5JT" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parable of the English speaker (Unfinished, will probably not be finished so it stands as is.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/sAkjSup026g?si=eosbHjKfchH5J3Fb" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><category term="Videos"></category></entry><entry><title>Francoforte</title><link href="/francoforte.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-04-10T10:20:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-04-10T19:30:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Bruno Teles</name></author><id>tag:None,2011-04-10:/francoforte.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Neo-noir financial film, where an investigator attempts to tackle the big issue of the day: the looming IMF intervention. Language: Portuguese with English subtitles&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A film I made with the help of some friends what seems to me a long time ago. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Language: Portuguese with English subtitles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neo-noir financial film, where an investigator attempts to tackle the big issue of the day: the looming IMF intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe title="vimeo-player" src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/58882236?h=47eb543803" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0"    allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><category term="Videos"></category></entry></feed>