<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Bruno's Website of Things - Development Blog</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/development-blog.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2023-08-30T17:03:09+01:00</updated><entry><title>Games Arena: New project first week update</title><link href="/games-arena-new-project-first-week-update.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-08-30T17:03:09+01:00</published><updated>2023-08-30T17:03:09+01:00</updated><author><name>Bruno Teles</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-08-30:/games-arena-new-project-first-week-update.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Django web application, project name Games Arena, week one update.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm starting a new project in Django, which is to be the final project of my Web Development with Python and Javascript course. Unlike other projects of that course, this one I will be doing from scratch, with no seed code. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This first week, I have initialized the django project and created a screen to choose your nickname. Once you do, or if you already have logged in before, it will take you to the Games Arena proper, where you'll be able to see who else is online so you can choose people to play a game. All this is done via sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment, being online is implemented only as a button which allows players to make themselves available for a game, but I'm looking to implement a way for the server to tell who is and isn't online automatically. I'm looking to do this via Redis. More news on that, or on my failure to do so, on my next update, I hope.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Development Blog"></category></entry><entry><title>Website: New project using Pelican</title><link href="/website-new-project-using-pelican.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-08-28T18:03:45+01:00</published><updated>2023-08-28T18:03:45+01:00</updated><author><name>Bruno Teles</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-08-28:/website-new-project-using-pelican.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;First update on new project, creating a website using Pelican&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm making a static website (this one) in which to keep the different parts of my internet presence organised, and also to help me figure out who am am? (Not not am, must not say am).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm using Pelican, a Python static website generator, and Markdown for the pages. Pelican is very easy to use. Having written websites in clunkier ways (my previous website, which dates from the early 2000s, was written entirely on raw HTML) I found it a breeze to create the content, layout and articles. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Documentation is short and very well written, with about everything you might need from a website like this. It lends itself to being configured to automate lots of things (such as the article type, category, date of publication and modification) as well as automatically reacting to a new file and, making the output HTML and serving it. So, after just a few tweaks, you're just writing really simple markdown files and saving them. This is a way of working I appreciate, but I'm also reassured I can change the fields being written automatically by manually including them, which I have been making use of to create an archive of past projects based on when I first released them, rather than the date of creation of the article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I've initialized my project, configured it to do what I need it to do, been trying out different themes and different functionalities. I like the way there's a base configuration that gets changed based on a smaller, easily readable file (at least so far, as I haven't changed that many parameters) which sets out what you need for testing and that there's a further file with config for when you actually go ahead and publish it. So far, it reads well and works well. Haven't brought it live yet, though, as I want to flesh out the content a little better before I do that, so I'll put a note here detailing how that went&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also been using virtualenv to create a virtual environment where I have installed pelican and markdown. This is something I plan to do going forward on other projects, as it is a much neater way to ensure you have what you need for a particular usecase without messing with other projects. I will be using that on the web app I'm developing as well, especially as I'll be working with a database (Redis) which I haven't used before, and I want to make sure I don't break things in the base configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's all for now!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Development Blog"></category></entry></feed>