<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Bruno's Website of Things - Reviews</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/reviews.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2023-08-27T18:19:22+01:00</updated><entry><title>Science and Sanity (not a review)</title><link href="/science-and-sanity-not-a-review.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-08-27T18:15:52+01:00</published><updated>2023-08-27T18:15:52+01:00</updated><author><name>Bruno Teles</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-08-27:/science-and-sanity-not-a-review.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Not really a review of a very long and technical book I haven't finished.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've never finished Science and Sanity, by Alfred Korzbski. I've barely made it a third of the way through, actually, having read it as closely as I possibly could, given the constraints of my life at the time. I'd say I made a proper attempt at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science and Sanity is an exposition of a system of thought, or a discipline, called General Semantics, which Korzybski founded. It's a massive book, and not an easy read (which Korzybski, in the introduction, recommends be read twice) which uses language updates of his own making (such as a full stop to mean, roughly, etc.). Why he does this is explained in the book. Since I have not even made it to the middle of the book, I should qualify all the statements below as characterizing what I understood of the rather than characterizing the system. I could add "as far as I can tell" to every sentence below, often a couple of times, but I'll inspire myself on the DRY principle and ask you to mentally append ", as far as I can tell" just before the full stop at the end of each sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It sets about a sketch of a group of changes in language which Korzybski proposes will be more "sane" which, in his use of the term, is synonimous with having the same structure of the world around. His most famous change is to proscribe the use of the verb to be in its capacity as verb of identity (basically, always, unless it's an auxiliary verb). The reasoning behind this is that verbs define relationships between things, and there's no such thing as an identity relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why I've redirected you here in my "about me" page. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reviews"></category></entry><entry><title>Do lots cry?</title><link href="/do-lots-cry.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-08-27T09:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-08-27T18:19:22+01:00</updated><author><name>Bruno Teles</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-08-27:/do-lots-cry.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Book review of The Crying of Lot 49, by Thomas Pynchon&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Spoilerish review of Thomas Pynchon's "The Crying of Lot 49". I wouldn't worry too much about spoilers here, but if you wnat to go without knowing absolutely anything, just go ahead and read it (spoiler for the review: I'm going to recommend it!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's funny. It's terrifying in a strange way, like a ghost story made believable. It is a virtuoso display of use of words, of the art of writing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's framed essentially as a detective novel, though there are no detectives, but a lowly executor of a will whose attempt at sorting the dead person's estate uncovers a great conspiracy or perhaps not quite. The novel lives for, perhaps demonstrate, this quantum-like "the electron is here and not here until we observe ita and collapse the wave function", in that we're never quite sure the conspiracy being uncovered is in any way real, and not the product of a paranoid mind (whose paranoid mind, the dead man or the executor, is also up for grabs.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also impossible not to mention the superb finale, though it would be too much to just explain it outright. Let us just say that, same as our main character uncovers the mystery, we uncover the mystery of the book title itself, a seemingly nonsensical sentence which we will, by the end, be assured not just of its meaning, but mainly, of its terrific importance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though perhaps not my favourite of the three Pynchon's I have read ("Bleeding Edge" takes that spot), it's short, and it does things some things too well, too well (by which I mean no other book does it quite like that) that it's essential to give it go. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So no excuses! Get it now at your local library or wherever you get your books.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reviews"></category></entry></feed>